Guide to the Judi Chapman Papers 1963-1999
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
Judi Chapman papers
1963-1999
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 641
Chapman, Judi, 1941-2000
12.7 linear feet
This collection consists primarily of subject and work files of Judi Chapman, assistant to US Representative Pat Williams of Montana from 1979-1991 and then lobbyist working largely with Native American tribes, including the Blackfeet and Havasupai.
Historical Note
Judith (Judi) Larson Chapman was born in Pierre, South Dakota on July 23, 1941. She graduated from St. Olaf College in 1963 and from The University of Montana with a degree in Social Work in 1974. Chapman served as an assistant to United States Representative Pat Williams of Montana’s 1st Congressional District from 1979-1991. As an assistant to Congressman Williams, Chapman dealt primarily with issues of women’s equality and Native American interests.
After her work with Representative Williams, Chapman was a lobbyist working largely with Native American tribes, including the Blackfeet Tribe (Montana) and the Havasupai Tribe (Arizona). She also conducted a number of lobbying workshops aimed at promoting Native American interests. In addition, Chapman held positions with the Administration of Native American Tribes, the Indian Head Start Program, and on the Monitoring and Evaluation team for Bureau of Indian Affairs schools.
Chapman was active with the Democratic Party, working on get-out-the-vote campaigns for the 1992 Presidential election and serving as a delegate to the 1996 Democratic National Convention. Chapman also served as a Missoula Democratic Central Committee Precinctwoman and was on a number of local boards related to environmental and Native American issues, including the Missoula City-County Health Board, the Missoula Air Pollution Control Board, the Missoula Water Quality Board, and the Indian Center.
Chapman passed away on July 19, 2000 in Missoula having battled brain cancer. She is survived by her daughters Tonia Anell Johnson Chapman Bossell and Varen Kay Johnson Chapman.
The Judi Chapman papers consist primarily of materials created from Chapman’s political work during the 1990s. This includes materials related to Chapman’s lobbying activities for the Blackfeet and Havasupai Tribes, administrative and informational materials for workshops on lobbying and the legislative process, notes relating to her work on the Missoula City-County Health Board, notes and correspondence created from her work with the Democratic Party, and files related to consultative work Chapman performed with Native American organizations in relation to grant writing. Also included are subject files supporting her work in various areas, many of which contain materials created during her years as an assistant to Pat Williams. This collection contains one series of materials created from Chapman’s work with the Mountain-Plains Education and Economic Development Program, a program designed to improve adult vocational education.
The Judi Chapman papers are generally arranged in alphabetic order, which generally reflects Chapman's original order. Discrepancies in the alphabetical arrangement reflect Chapman's deviation from alphabetic order. Certain discrepancies were maintained when clear relationships could be drawn between adjacent files. For example, a file titled "105th Congress" was kept with other files related to Congress. Published materials and instruction manuals were removed from the collection unless created or annotated by Chapman.
The Judi Chapman papers are organized into seven series:
Series I: Lobbying, 1985-1994, 1.5 linear feet
Subseries 1: Blackfeet Nation, 1985-1993, 1.3 linear feet
Subseries 2: Havasupai Tribe, 1993-1994, 0.2 linear feet
Series II: Workshops, 1989-1999, 1.4 linear feet
Subseries 1: Administrative files, 1986-1998, 0.9 linear feet
Subseries 2: Subject files, 1989-1999, 0.5 linear feet
Series III: Indian Organizations, 1972-1999, 3.9 linear feet
Subseries 1: Subject files, 1972-1996, 1.4 linear feet
Subseries 2: American Indian Higher Education Consortium, 1995-1996, 0.6 linear feet
Subseries 3: Grants and Head Start reviews, 1991-1999, 1.9 linear feet
Series IV: City of Missoula and Missoula County, 0.1 linear feet
Series V: Democratic Party, 1982-1997, 2.2 linear feet
Series VI: Subject files, 1963-1999, 2.8 linear feet
Subseries 1: General subject files, 1963-1999, 1.0 linear feet
Subseries 2: Native American subject files, 1982-1995, 1.8 linear feet
Series VII: Mountain-Plains Education and Economic Development Program, 1972-1973, 0.8 linear feet
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
Archives and Special Collections acquired the collection on June 5, 2006 from Varen Chapman and Tonia Bossell.
Related materials may be found in the following collection:
Pat Williams Papers (Mss 239), Archives & Special Collections, Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Chapman, Judi, 1941-2000; Williams, Pat, 1937-
United States. Congress. House.; Democratic Party (U.S.); Missoula City-County Health Dept.; Mountain-Plains Education and Economic Development Program.; aUniversity of Montana--Missoula--Alumni and alumnae.
Blackfeet Tribe of the Blackfeet Indian Reservation of Montana.; Havasupai Tribe of the Havasupai Reservation, Arizona.; Montana--Politics and government--20th century.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; United States--Politics and government--1989-1993.
Havasupai Indians.; Indians of North America--Government relations--1934-; Indians of North America--Arizona.; Indians of North America--Montana.; Lobbying--United States.; Siksika Indians.; Vocational education--West (U.S.); Women--Political activity--Montana.
Sound recordings
Civic Activism; Native Americans; Political Campaigns; Missoula; Montana
Lobbyists--United States.; Women political activists--United States.; aWomen political consultants--United States.
- Lobbying, 1985-1994; Series I; 1.5 linear feet
  This series contains materials related to Chapman’s career as a lobbyist. This includes files used for workshops that she led for several Native American groups. Chapman’s primary work as a lobbyist was in conjunction with the Blackfeet Indians in Montana. This series also includes materials documenting her work with the Havasupai, a tribe based in Supai, which is located in northwest Arizona. As a lobbyist, Chapman worked on a host of issues including improvements with regards to Native American housing, legal systems, education, and water infrastructure. This series is divided into three subseries: Blackfeet Nation, Havasupai Tribe, and Workshops.
  - Blackfeet Nation, 1985-1993; Subseries 1; 1.3 linear feet
    This subseries contains materials related to Chapman’s extensive work with the Blackfeet Indians. This includes correspondence, notes, and subject files used to advance legislation on law enforcement, education, health care, and emergency disaster assistance. Also included are materials regarding Blackfeet issues predating Chapman’s career as a lobbyist that were likely gathered when Chapman was an assistant to Representative Pat Williams. In addition, this subseries contains files related to voter mobilization efforts amongst the Blackfeet in 1992. These efforts are likely related to her work with the Montana Alliance for Progressive Policy’s get out the vote campaign.
    - Notebooks, circa 1994 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Correspondence, 1991 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Drilling near Badger-Two Medicine, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Emergency disaster assistance, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Essential tribal services, 1991 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Head Start, 1991 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Indian health care amendments, 1991 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Last Star Homes, 1991 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Law Enforcement, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Legislation, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 2/1-2)
    - Legislation, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 2/3-6)
    - Legislation (continued), 1990-1992 (Box-folder 3/1-2)
    - Model Trust Department, 1992 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Montana Conservation Corps, 1991 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Monthly and quarterly reports and contracts, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Senate Bill 1696, 1992 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Staggered terms, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Testimony and appropriations, 1993 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Treaties, 1985 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Tribal Cattle Herd Pilot Project - TRICAPP, 1990 (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Tribal minutes, 1992 (Box-folder 3/11)
    - Voting, 1992 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Havasupai Tribe, 1993-1994; Subseries 2; 0.2 linear feet
    This subseries contains materials for Chapman’s work to advance the Havasupai Tribal Water Development Project from 1993-1994. Included are correspondence, notes, reports, and subject files related to the project.
    - Copies – correspondence legislation meeting summary re: Bar Four Water, 1993 (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Correspondence, 1994 (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Hualapai Hilltop and Bar Four - Havasupai Master Plan, 1991 (Box-folder 26/1)
    - Notes on 1976 report, undated (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Notes on Havasupai project, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Weekly Reports – regarding Havasupai Water Development at Hilltop and Bar Four, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 4/7)
- Workshops, 1989-1998; Series II; 1.4 linear feet
  This series contains subject files, correspondence, and notes used by Chapman for her lobbying workshops. Chapman led workshops for tribes located in Montana, Washington, South Dakota, and Alaska, as well as for national organizations such as the American Indian Higher Education Consortium.
  - Administrative files, 1986-1998; Subseries 1; 0.9 linear feet
    This subseries contains evaluations, notes regarding the general structure of Chapman’s workshop, and notes for specific workshops.
    - Chugach – notes on workshop, 1997 (Box-folder 4/8)
    - Curriculum development and power organizations, undated (Box-folder 4/9)
    - Evaluations, 1986-1993 (Box-folder 4/10)
    - Evaluations – workshop materials development notes, circa 1993 (Box-folder 4/11)
    - Dead jobs, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 4/12)
    - Kaufman and Associates, 1993 (Box-folder 4/13)
    - KRA, 1998 (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Lonefight and Associates – Correspondence and misc., 1994 (Box-folder 5/2)
    - MIEA (Montana Indian Education Association) – Dan Williams, 1996 (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Native American Technology – correspondence and proposals, 1995-1998 (Box-folder 5/4)
    - NISBA (National Indian School Board Administration) – How a Bill becomes Law, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Other Areas, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Bonnie Paquin – correspondence, 1991-1994 (Box-folder 5/7)
    - Racism workshops research file, 1998 (Box-folder 5/8)
    - Rapid City workshop – notes and materials, 1994 (Box-folder 5/9)
    - Rego II – consultants, 1995 (Box-folder 5/10)
    - RJS and Associates, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 5/11)
    - Salish Kootenai College – correspondence, 1997 (Box-folder 6/1)
    - Tribal Education Contractors Association, 1993-1996 (Box-folder 6/2)
    - Working efficiently with tribes, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 6/3)
    - Workshop advertising, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 6/4)
    - Workshop materials, 1989-1994 (Box-folder 6/5)
    - Workshop schedule – materials, personal notes, 1994 (Box-folder 6/6)
    - Workshop schedule - Day 1, circa 1994 (Box-folder 6/7)
    - Workshop schedule - Day 2, circa 1994 (Box-folder 6/8)
    - Workshop schedule - Day 3, circa 1994 (Box-folder 6/9)
  - Subject files, 1989-1998; Subseries 2; 0.5 linear feet
    This subseries contains subject files Chapman used in support of her workshop. The subject files concern the Federal legislative process, lobbying, and files specifically dedicated to Native American issues.
    - Anti–Indian organizations, undated (Box-folder 6/10)
    - Appropriations – glossary of terms and departments, undated (Box-folder 6/11)
    - Budget - 1995 priority ranking (Box-folder 6/12)
    - Budget information, 1989-1995 (Box-folder 6/13)
    - Budget process, 1995 (Box-folder 6/14)
    - Capitol Hill, undated (Box-folder 6/15)
    - Committee on Natural Resources, 1993 (Box-folder 6/16)
    - Congress – general information, structure committees pertinent to Indians press, 1982-1990 (Box-folder 6/17)
    - 105th Congress – press clippings, Dorsey Weekly, 1997 (Box-folder 6/18)
    - Congress - structure, undated (Box-folder 7/1)
    - Consultants, 1980-1991 (Box-folder 7/2)
    - Effective Interaction – effectively working with Congress workshop materials, undated (Box-folder 7/3)
    - Executive Branch, undated (Box-folder 7/4)
    - Facilitation – materials from CERT training, undated (Box-folder 7/5)
    - Follow up, undated (Box-folder 7/6)
    - Four kinds of Legislation – workshop materials, undated (Box-folder 7/7)
    - How a Bill Becomes Law, 1995 (Box-folder 7/8)
    - Interpersonal communication with power figures notes, undated (Box-folder 7/9)
    - Interviewing – sample, undated (Box-folder 7/10)
    - Legislative cartoon, undated (Box-folder 7/11)
    - Legislative information, circa 1992 (Box-folder 7/12)
    - Legislative packet, undated (Box-folder 7/13)
    - Legislative process, undated (Box-folder 7/14)
    - Letters - sample, 1992 (Box-folder 7/15)
    - Letters to editors, undated (Box-folder 7/16)
    - Lobbying - general, 1989-1995 (Box-folder 7/17)
    - Lobbying by letter, undated (Box-folder 7/18)
    - Lobbying by personal contact, 1995 and undated (Box-folder 7/19)
    - Lobbying by telephone, undated (Box-folder 7/20)
    - Lobbying packet, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 7/21)
    - Lobbying rules, undated (Box-folder 7/22)
      Folder title: So You Want to be a Lobbyist
    - Missoula County Indians Pat Williams election, 1992 (Box-folder 7/23)
    - Montana Congressional delegation, undated (Box-folder 7/24)
    - Montana delegation for Indian affairs, 1991 (Box-folder 7/25)
    - Office of Management and Budget, 1993 (Box-folder 7/26)
    - Once Upon a Time, undated (Box-folder 7/27)
    - Protocol, 1982-1994 (Box-folder 7/28)
    - Right to write, undated (Box-folder 7/29)
    - SCIA - Senate Committee on Indian Affairs staff list, 1995-1998 (Box-folder 7/30)
    - Terminology, undated (Box-folder 7/31)
    - Testimony, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 7/32)
    - Tracking tools, 1993 (Box-folder 7/33)
    - Tribal budget and system process, 1995 (Box-folder 7/34)
    - Tribal government – definition, undated (Box-folder 7/35)
- Indian organizations, 1972-1999; Series III; 3.9 linear feet
  This series contains materials related to Chapman’s work with the Administration for Native Americans (ANA), the Indian Headstart Program, and American Indian Higher Education Consortium (AIHEC). Chapman served as a reader for grant proposals submitted to the ANA and as an on-site reviewer for the Indian Headstart Program. Chapman also worked with the AIHEC to develop a database providing information for several Tribal colleges.
  - Subject files, 1972-1996; Subseries 1; 1.4 linear feet
    This subseries consists of subject files related to Chapman’s work with Native American organizations.
    - Air – Clean Air Act, 1994 (Box-folder 7/36)
    - Administration for Native Americans, 1990-1994 (Box-folder 7/37)
    - Administration for Native Americans reader guidelines, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Alaska, 1986-1994 (Box-folder 8/2)
    - American Indian Caucus, 1983 (Box-folder 8/3)
    - American Indian Movement, 1975-1994 (Box-folder 8/4)
    - American Indian Policy Review, 1977-1982 (Box-folder 8/5)
    - American Indian drug abuse - Indian Alcohol and Drug Program data, 1986-1992 (Box-folder 8/6)
    - American Indian Religious Freedom Act - HR 1546 AIRFA Amendments, 1978-1991 (Box-folder 8/7)
    - American Indian Sustainable Homelands, 1992 (Box-folder 8/8)
    - Anti-Indian, 1984-1993 (Box-folder 8/9)
    - Appropriations for 1994 (Box-folder 8/10)
    - Appropriations – general, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 8/11)
    - Appropriations – Impact on American Indians, 1990-1993 (Box-folder 8/12)
    - Blackfeet, 1992 (Box-folder 8/13)
    - Block grants, 1981-1986 (Box-folder 9/1)
    - Brendale versus the Confederated Tribes and Bands of the Yakima Indian Nation, 1989 (Box-folder 9/2)
    - Budget, 1977-1990 (Box-folder 9/3)
    - Reagan budgets, undated (Box-folder 9/4)
    - Reconciliation – health care budget, 1980, 1991 (Box-folder 9/5)
    - Buffy’s Song lyrics, undated (Box-folder 9/6)
    - Bureau of Indian Affairs, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 9/7)
    - Facilities management - Bureau of Indian Affairs, 1990 (Box-folder 9/8)
    - Indian Business, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 9/9)
    - Business - Indian Business Development Grants, 1989, 1992 (Box-folder 9/10)
    - Child abuse, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 9/11)
      overnight hearing on Indian Child Abuse Prevention and Treatment Act
    - Child care, 1990 (Box-folder 9/12)
    - Civil jurisdiction – Non-Indians, 1989 (Box-folder 9/13)
    - Indian civil rights, 1979-1991 (Box-folder 9/14)
    - Clean Water Act – tribal participation in Clean Water Act, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 9/15)
    - Christopher Columbus, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 9/16)
    - Commission on Reservation Economy – recommendations, undated (Box-folder 9/17)
    - Community involvement – Administration for Native Americans, 1993 (Box-folder 9/18)
    - 98th Congress – congressional and legislative affair. Staff Report Dept. of Interior 1984 Indian Affairs Legislation enacted or considered (Box-folder 9/19)
    - 99th Congress, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 9/20)
    - 101st Congress – Legislative Update, Personal Notes to Congressman Pat Williams regarding Indian Legislation; Bilss Stauts report (Indian) Accomplishments; Highlights, Civil Liberties in the 101st Congress summary of major legislation, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 9/21)
    - 103rd Congress – Directory, Legislative Update, 1993 (Box-folder 9/22)
    - 104th Congress – Dorsey Weekly, update on Indian Legislation, 1996 (Box-folder 9/23)
    - Consultation – Indian Consultation participation in legislative process Council of Energy Resource Tribes (CERT), 1990-1991 (Box-folder 9/24)
    - Courts - Tribal Courts, 1991 (Box-folder 10/1)
    - Courts - Tribal Judicial Conference – Discussion paper on the Creation of Tribal Judicial Conference, 1992 (Box-folder 10/2)
    - Courts - Tribal Justice Act – memos, legislation notes, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 10/3)
    - Crow and Creek schools., 1993 (Box-folder 10/4)
    - Cultural awareness position paper, undated (Box-folder 10/5)
    - Indian cultural groups in North Dakota, 1972 (Box-folder 10/6)
    - Dances with Wolves, 1990-1993 (Box-folder 10/7)
    - Albert Duro – 11-13-90 news clippings – Resolution to all tribal jurisdictions over non-tribal members on Reservations etc., 1990-1991 (Box-folder 10/8)
    - Economic development, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 10/9)
    - Education, 1982-1993 (Box-folder 10/10-11)
    - ACTS - Association of Contract Tribal Schools, 1986 (Box-folder 10/12)
    - Education - Indian adult education, 1992 (Box-folder 10/13)
    - Education - National Indian Education Association, 1990-1996 (Box-folder 10/14)
    - Indian and Native American Employment and Training Coalition, 1982-1996 (Box-folder 11/1)
  - American Indian Higher Education Consortium, 1990-1996; Subseries 2; 0.6 linear feet
    This subseries consists of notes, correspondence, and materials generated by Chapman concerning the creation of a database linking Tribal colleges.
    - AIHEC - American Indian Higher Education Consotrium database, 1995 (Box-folder 11/2)
      memos and data
    - National Commission on Libraries and Information Services to Native Americans, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 11/3-6)
    - National Commission on Libraries and Information Services to Native Americans (continued), 1990-1992 (Box-folder 12/1-3)
    - Montana Indian Education Association (MIEA), 1996 (Box-folder 12/4)
  - Grants and Head Start reviews, 1991-1999; Subseries 3; 1.9 linear feet
    This subseries is an unprocessed group of materials created from Chapman’s work with Native American tribes as a grant reader for the ANA, as a consultant working to help Native American organizations create successful grants, and as a reviewer of Headstart Programs for the Bureau of Indian Affairs. Folder names reflect titles from the original collection inventory.
    - National Indian Health Board, 1996 (Box 27)
      Budget, Memos, FAX Communications
    - Black Hills – Black Hills American Indian Center, 1991-1996 (Box 27)
    - Administration for Native Americans Panel reviewer information, undated (Box 27)
    - Loud Thunder International, undated (Box 27)
      Administration for Native Americans application by Loud Thunder International to fund the Montana Ojibwa Tribal Preservation project. The project purpose is cultural preservation through restoration of tribal status and restoration of relationship with American government; personal notes, memos, proposal.
    - Echota Cherokee Administration for Native Americans application for grant to preserve native language – Application, memos responses., undated (Box 27)
    - Montana Tribal Business Information Network, undated (Box 27)
      Administration for Native Americans proposal, memos, letters of support, personal notes.
    - First American Resources and Services, 1996 (Box 27)
      Administration for Native Americans Proposal 1996 – Planning for urban Economic Self – Sufficiency – memos, personal notes, proposal
    - American Indian Business leaders, undated (Box 28)
      Administration for Native Americans proposal, memos, personal notes review
    - Haliwa – Sapori Indian Tribe, undated (Box 28)
      Administration for Native Americans proposal 1996, -memos, personal notes, review
    - Pohatan Renape Nation, undated (Box 28)
    - North Plains Chemical Dependency, 1996 (Box 28)
      Administration for Native Americans proposal content outline 1996
    - Native American Center - Great Falls, undated (Box 28)
      Administration for Native Americans proposal application memos
    - National Jobs Training Partnership Act (JTPA) Conference Providence, Rhode Island, 1997 (Box 28)
    - Nurses Association, 1997 (Box 28)
      American Indian Nursing Summit notes for workshop
    - In Care Network, undated (Box 28)
      Administration for Native Americans proposal, review
    - Indian Vocational Education – Reviewer information 1995, undated (Box 28)
    - Head Start on-site review, undated (Box 28)
      1993-1995 program review materials, news clippings, memos, personal notes
    - Head Start expansion, 1998 (Box 28)
    - Choctaw – Head Start Conference, 1995-1996 (Box 29)
      on site program review materials
    - Conference Salish and Kootenai, undated (Box 29)
      on site program visit materials
    - Creek, 1996 (Box 29)
      site review materials
    - Kickapoo, 1995 (Box 29)
      Head Start on site review materials
    - Muskogee, 1996 (Box 29)
      Creek nation information sheet; Head Start review
    - Navajo, 1995 (Box 29)
    - Stone Container Corporation, undated (Box 29)
    - Three Affiliated Tribes, 1995 (Box 29)
    - Department of Education Vocational Education, 1995 (Box 29)